so anna this is very sad you cheated on
me
you were playing with another coach
while i was gone in germany
and he started like teaching me he said
i teach you forehand and what do you say
again he said i am
i started learning tennis yeah as an
adult so i shouldn't be
practicing loop because my brain doesn't
get enough speed to process this
information okay he said
just be here and
simplicity yeah
and look so
what
he's not 100 wrong
you could hit a forehand like you were
doing in a very early on when we first
started remember no but he didn't like
that
thing when i was like just
losing it here he said just
that like a like a no loop basically not
doing anything take the rackets take the
racquet straight back in other words
without a loop right
it's not necessarily wrong to hit a
forehand like that people back in the
day used to play like that that's a
classic tennis right right so you can
play like that but it is absolutely no
comparison to what's called a modern
forehand right when it comes to all
aspects of the forehand whether you're
talking about
topspin
control and most importantly power it is
absolutely no comparison whatsoever so
you get a lot more control with the
modern forehand you got a lot more power
it also feels a lot better that forehand
it's more rhythmic it's more continuous
so it's a question that every
recreational player should ask
themselves
you want to optimize your game just a
big question do you want to play the to
the best of your abilities you do right
i do i think everybody does i started
feeling the taste of this beautiful
movement yeah no you're doing good if
you take a look at your match do you see
your match when you play christine
you're doing a beautiful job on the
forehand and you know what it was like
the ball was coming at you a little bit
slower so you had more time
and it was working beautifully so it's
coming along we just have to be patient
ball machine was surprising you and
there was surprising but my loop there
was was fun
even better so that's the question if
you want to optimize your game and play
to the best of your abilities you got to
do what's called a modern forehand so no
you shouldn't go like this and take the
racket straight back no don't do that
lana look your forehand at times
especially when you hit hard like i
already told you it's kind of like it's
not your fault you're not doing it on
purpose the wrist kind of comes through
right here
come right back at me
we're gonna slow it down we gotta hit
slowly
go again
slow down like 30
slow down
very nice
okay not too
fast good
okay like this yeah it's kind of it kind
of comes through a little bit not all
the time sometimes when you hit super
hard that's why i tell you slow down 10
slow down 20
or even slow down 30 to 50 percent but
the more you slow down the more you're
going to be able to feel what's going on
around the contact
and that brings me to the top spin
that's how we're going to i'm going to
teach you top spin is by slowing it way
down we're going to slow down like 75
we're going to play mini tennis and
basically what you're going to do when
it's top spin is there's going to be
more of a vertical swing path so you're
not going to go like this
you're going to go more like this see
the racquet goes up watch this the
racquet is going to go up you see that
that's top spin watch racket's going up
that's top spin now this is flat watch
this is flat you see how the rack is
going more horizontal now if you take a
look at the ball what the ball is doing
on the court
this is top spin
you see that
watch this is top spin okay watch the
ball here follow the ball this is top
spin
you see the ball
see how it's bouncing like higher it's
going higher over the net
and this is flat watch this ball watch
this
so it's flat you see this is flat
this is very flat
so when you hit flat and you hit super
hard it's not wrong to hit flat but the
control is difficult so you're gonna
start hitting the net it's gonna start
going long like you almost have to hit
the perfect every time so with topspin
it gives you a little bit more room for
error you know yeah you're staying on
the ball
a millisecond longer it changes the
control it makes it better
also the ball
the gravity will work for you in your
favor because the ball is spinning so
much the gravity will pull it in a
little bit faster so it will fly more on
a on a curve right as opposed to
straight like this
so it's more control so what i want you
to do we're going to go right here on
the service line and then come right
here i want to show you the swing path
here just imagine you're hitting all
right so i'm gonna show you this one pat
you're gonna come here don't make your
arm so stiff
you're gonna go here like this you're
just gonna go here to the shoulder but
you're gonna be more vertical
like that okay
yeah you're coming through a little more
so go up to the service line now
remember as far as your modern forehand
all that nothing changes you're just
changing how you're going to strike the
ball
you're going to go a little bit more
vertical nothing else changes everything
stays the same
also it doesn't mean that you can never
hit flat forehands those are fine but on
a situation like this where we're just
trying to keep the ball in play and work
on consistency
the top spin is going to be very
important yeah but besides i hit a lot
of them on my sides of the cord exactly
upsetting
come right here and now you're just
gonna you're gonna come vertically over
the ball
and there's a few tricks along the way
that we can increase the top spin here
we go
okay come again
okay it's it's a little bit better just
keep going yeah it's it's better
better
come again i'm just
trying to figure it out okay watch this
we're gonna do it together yeah let's
watch this someone's making up so stiff
so i can move it
you see that
you see it's a little bit more vertical
here this way but you're still not you
know
moving your wrist no no what you could
do you could do it with the wrist
you could do it with the wrist but the
problem with that is number one you can
hurt yourself because your wrist if you
move it fast you can hurt yourself also
the ball it's gonna very little power so
if you just come over the ball like this
you're shortening everything and you're
isolating this movement nothing else is
happening with the body you're just
making topspin right here with the with
the wrist and it's very weak part of the
body so there's gonna be limited power
and it's gonna be a lot of frame shots
as well because you're drastically
changing the angle of the racket face at
the moment of contact so don't use the
wrist rather with the entire body try to
generate a vertical swim pad whether
you're trying to make the body more
straight or you you're imagining going
up with the arm like this coming from
the shoulder pulling more from the
shoulder as if you were pulling a cable
upwards in the gym
these are good thoughts to have but
rolling the wrist like this like a
doorknob because it's not good that's
what i feel like the motion is coming
from it can feel like that if you if you
turn the wrist over a little bit after
contact it's going to feel like that too
if you go like this see that right there
it looks like i'm using wrist but i'm
not
it's the wrist starts coming through
here
but i'm still not using it at contact
like that
now another thing that we can do
we're gonna get to that later i don't
want to throw too many things at you so
just picture more of a vertical swing
path that's the key
as vertical as possible
you imagine a wall in front of you you
hit very slowly on us slowly
batter do it again top spin it
good and again
but the preparation is the same
everything's the same object
everything's the same nothing changes
not a single thing everything stays
exactly the same
good here we go
not so hard you're hitting too hard you
won't listen the faster you do it the
more you play with your intuition
because the stroke becomes more
intuitive the faster it goes in order
for you to make changes around the
contact you got to slow your stroke way
down i'm talking 30 percent max
otherwise it's going to trying to hack
it and then slow down no you want
usually
my intuition knows
it won't work that way it won't work
that way i guarantee here we go
good and go up all the way come on
best one so far that was yeah i actually
moved my body now
and yeah i did
what that's what i told you before
whatever it takes to make the racket go
more vertical use your body to make that
happen no doubt about it and this is
also robot
same right everything's the same nothing
changes
let's not complicate things now we got
to do one step at a time okay
here we go
better
best one so far you hear the spin
it felt like spin yeah all right now the
racket was vibrating too it was fun
absolutely now let's do one more thing
we're going to imagine
going a little bit lower with the racket
and going a little bit higher what i
want you to focus on is going from your
hip
to your shoulder from the hip to the
shoulder you mean here with your hand
all right the hand goes from the hip to
the shoulder so when the ball is on
above your hand
now you're going to have to go up to
meet the ball and generally it's easier
to continue going up if you start from a
lower point yeah that makes sense so if
you go from your hip the balls are right
here a little bit above your hip you're
going to go up and then you're likely
going to continue to go up okay
so from the hip
to the shoulder here we go
oh my goodness yes so good it works
vibrate
anna you're doing tough
you're doing top spin
there was not much top spin there you
went like this again here we go
you hear the sound of the space that's
top spin yeah very nice job
it's going to help you with control yeah
dramatically all right let's pick them
up quickly we'll go to baseline okay
okay remember that now when we're the
baseline we're trying to do this
naturally from the baseline you have to
hit harder and faster otherwise the ball
won't make it over the net so there's a
likelihood that you're going to go back
a little bit to your old forehand i'm
telling you
i'm telling you this now because it's a
lot easier to put spin from the service
line therefore we need to do a lot of
mini tennis to learn top spin tons of
mini tennis and i even encourage you
that when you practice by yourself you
do it very close to the net or close to
the wall or ball machine or whatever it
may be
because the closer you are the softer
you can hit the more control
over the contact point you have
and you can learn this shot from scratch
much better as you start hitting harder
as you go back into the chord as you try
to get depth on the ball your intuition
takes over and the stroke has a tendency
to flatten out more so there's gonna be
a test let's see whether you can do this
from the baseline i think you can well i
was just programmed negatively now
no no listen i am just joking
it's not it's not it's like i just want
to make sure that you understand there's
nothing wrong with a flat forehand and
you can use both you can hit with
topspin if you want to you can hit hit
flat flat is great if you're like
feeling like you're playing well you
have good timing
flat is the best way to hit winners it's
your fastest forehand it's going to be
much faster than your tops and forehand
so there's still a time and a place for
flats
but on days like today where we're
really trying to grind we're trying to
keep the ball going back and forth as
much as possible this is where tops can
help you tremendously or if you play a
match and you're feeling a little bit
nervous or tight that's where topspin is
gonna be your friend all right here we
go
from the hip to the shoulder and this is
looking good
not too fast
back up just a little bit all right
that's beautiful
here we go
now if you want i'm actually watching
the ball as it's flying and i can see it
rotating i can see the ball going like
this so i can tell how much spin it has
on it
okay yeah can you there's something that
i recommend to students as well you kind
of track your own ball as it's flying
and you can see how much spinning is on
there yeah
that was maybe the best forehand you hit
today that was beautiful topspin see i'm
figuring it out oh good good good for
serving the balls nice here we go
and watch that ball spin that one had
tons of spin on it was it oh yeah what i
was here and i completely relaxed my
wrist while i was going down and then i
tensed it up when it needed to be all
right
look i'm not a big fan of i'm not a big
fan of like work manipulating the wrist
either way whether you're loosening it
or tightening it i like it to be natural
but if that worked for you continue
doing that
if that if that's something that you it
works for you continue doing it
you know what i did i just did a
continental grip yeah all right
that's classic forehand by the way
no oh again
come on
it's a little too much wrist movement
ana now the forehand is completely gone
yeah now what do you think happened you
like five shots ago you started talking
about the wrist right put the wrist out
of your mind okay because now you ruined
your forehand now you're all wristy it's
not you're not even getting any spin
okay and the ball is going way out
so don't yeah get out of your head keep
it natural don't think about it it's
going to be right by itself if you think
about it whether you're loosening or
tightening it tell me some stories from
youtube
all right so anna did you watch my q a
video yes i like it oh you saw it yes
okay all right actually yeah i will uh
all right do the comment on that it was
very hard i asked ask ask me a question
i'll answer it in my q a
no no no i can't think i can
this is fascinating because now we
put your mind away from the from the
wrist we started talking about something
else look what happened here you see how
it stabilized on its own yeah
do you believe me now sometimes like an
obstacle to be so cerebral
well you don't you over you are someone
who likes to over analyze and over
overthink a little bit yeah and that's
not good when it comes to tennis
technique yeah or dancing is that right
yeah yeah i can imagine if you are
thinking about your feet too much you
get all mechanical
but you probably look mechanical on a
dance floor right yeah it doesn't look
smooth right
all right here we go
fabulous do it again
nice top spin
okay
when you cut a little towards the frame
yeah
go again
i know this is perfect
anna that one right there you came from
underneath a little more you see how you
whipped that up you actually hit it
quite fast you went really fast that's
called topspin forehand very nice job
okay
now i'm gonna hit with you we're gonna
try to do the same thing actually not
hit but feed first i'm going to feed you
some balls okay and you stay right here
in a baseline you try to do top spin
beautiful top spin ana there it is
whoa
you mean the racket drop
yeah it was a part of the loop and i
just noticed it if you come from
underneath more it's easier
if you come even under the hip
you can do that too if you want yeah now
i didn't tell you that because it's a
little bit more extreme there's a little
bit more movement there in the wrist
when you go underneath the wrist has to
bend in a different direction
but that's another thing that you can do
you can drop the wrist even drop the
drop the racket head a little lower and
now it's a lot easier to make spin so
generally if you come more from
underneath the ball
spin is easier
so keep doing it if you like it here we
go
good
good anna
oh lala this is crazy this is crazy
anna this is insane
fabulous on a fabulous forehand topspin
yes
what do you think
i like it it works
this is so cool
you understand
but do you understand the different
sound the ball makes like it's spinning
more you can feel the control right yeah
now i want to tell you it's losing power
though so so well it's not as fast as
your flat forehand but what happens
is that eventually when you get a lot of
confidence in this forehand you'll be
able to swing faster maybe it's also
because i'm not using it maybe maybe a
little bit but generally when any time
you put top spin the ball is spinning
more and it will lose speed as it's
traveling to the other side
but that allows you because it's more
controlling that allows you to swing a
lot faster so indirectly topspin has
more power but yeah no you you're doing
great this was really i'm very surprised
you learned
the topspin very fast
so we continue we're going to continue
doing this this is going to be this is
going to be great for you yeah because a
lot of my balls they come to internet
and also go long especially get
breastfeed here they go now i see all of
them are in they go a little higher than
that they dip in
some consistency yeah nice work
like this there you go
you